A Guide to the George Rust, Jr. Papers, 1788, 1815-1858
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Papers, 1788, 1815-1858
Library of Virginia
24688
.225 cubic feet
George Rust, Jr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 2 November 1957.
Biographical Information
George Rust, Jr., was born 4 January 1788 in Virginia to George Rust (1760-1850) and Elizabeth Rust (ca. 1766-1844). He lived for a while in Prince George's County, Maryland for a few years and was one of the defenders of Baltimore, Maryland, during the War of 1812. He moved to Loudoun County, Virginia, and represented that county in the House of Delegates from 1819 to 1823. Rust was elected brigadier general of the Virginia militia by the Virginia legislature in January 1824. During the 1828 presidential election, he was an elector for Andrew Jackson and John C. Calhoun. Rust served as superintendent of the United States Armory at Harper's Ferry, (West) Virginia, from 1830 to 1837. Rust was a planter and a businessman, owning part interest in a shoe and hat store in Baltimore from 1840 to 1845, and became a partner in a bank in Baltimore in 1856. Rust built "Rocklands" in Loudoun County, and then purchased "Exeter" in the same county. He and his nephew Albert Rust (ca. 1818-1870) also purchased the plantation "Indian Town" in Lancaster County, Virginia, in 1856. Rust married Maria Clagett Marlow (1790-1863) 8 November 1809 in Prince George's County, and they had nine children. Rust died 18 September 1857 in Baltimore, and was buried in Union Cemetery in Leesburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1788, 1815-1858, of George Rust, Jr. (1788-1857) of Loudoun County, Virginia, consisting of personal and business records containing accounts, advertisements, agreements, bonds, broadsides, calling cards, circular letters, correspondence, deeds, insurance policies, land patents, letters of introduction and recommendation, lists, petitions, powers of attorney, promissory notes, receipts, surveys, and tax records. Collection is divided into three series. Series I: Correspondence, 1815-1856. Series II: Business papers, 1811-1858. Series III: Business papers, 1788, 1815-1858.
Correspondence, 1815-1856, consists of letters to and from Rust and covers Virginia politics, national politics, turnpikes in Virginia, duelling, carriages, home furnishings, the Virginia militia, the United States Armory at Harper's Ferry, (West) Virginia, Rust's possible move to Louisiana, and personal and business matters. Of particular interest are letters from Armistead T. Mason to Rust concerning his carriage and home decor; a letter from James Pleasants to William S. Archer announcing Mason's death in a duel; letters congratulating Rust on being elected brigadier general in command of the 6th brigade of the Virginia militia; letters from Joseph Lewis and Edward Lucas concerning state and national politics; letters concerning Rust's considered move to Louisiana; letters to President Franklin Pierce recommending individuals for government positions; and letters from Albert Rust concerning their plantation "Indian Town" in Lancaster County, Virginia.
Business papers, 1811-1858, contain accounts, advertisements, bonds, broadsides, insurance policies, letters, lists, petitions, promissory notes, receipts, and tax records. Of particular interest: a letter from "Robison Cruso" to the mechanics at Harper's Ferry, (West) Virginia, concerning their work situation; accounts for supplies purchased for the United States Armory at Harper's Ferry; broadside from George Westinghouse and Company for farm equipment; insurance policy to Rust from Washington County Mutual Insurance Company; receipts for payment for stocks in the Alexandria, Loudoun, and Hampshire Railroad; list of slaves at Rust's plantation "Exeter" in Loudoun County; and petition from William Brannan to the Virginia legislature requesting a divorce.
Business papers, 1788, 1819-1858, consisting of accounts, advertisements, agreements, bonds, calling cards, circulars, deeds, land patents, lists, memorandums, notices, powers of attorney, promissory notes, receipts, surveys, and tax receipts. Of particular interest: land patent from Governor Edmund Randolph to Goldsmith Chandley for 500 acres in Monongalia County, (West) Virginia; power of attorney to Rust from the Leesburg Turnpike Company; 1820 deed for slaves; agreements for construction of buildings at the United States Armory at Harper's Ferry; list of salaries due workers; circular from Board of Public Works; agreements between Rust, Francis D. Dungan, and Thomas C. Watkins to open a shoe and hat business in Baltimore, Maryland; advertisement for sale of "Exeter" in Loudoun County; and papers concerning "Indian Town" in Lancaster County, Virginia, including deeds and lists of slaves.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Items are arranged chronologically within each series.
Organization
Organized into three series: Series I: Correspondence, 1815-1856. Series II: Buiness papers, 1811-1858. Series III: Business papers, 1788, 1819-1858.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1815-1856 (Folder 1-7)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Folder 1)
    - Letter, 5 July n.y., [Henry?] Edmundson to Gen. George Rust, Harper's Ferry, Virginia, a; 4 pages
    - Letter, n.d., Armistead T. Mason [Goshen] to George Rust, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, b; 2 pages
    - Letter, n.d.,A[rmistead] T. Mason to George Rust, c; 2 pages
    - Letter, n.d., George Rust to the Secretary of the Interior [possibly Robert McClelland], d; 1 leaf
    - Letter, n.d., George Rust to the Secretary of the Interior [possibly Robert McClelland], e; 1 leaf
    - Letter, n.d., George Rust to the President of the United States [Franklin Pierce], f; 1 leaf
    - Letter, n.d., George Rust to the President of the United States [Franklin Pierce], g; 1 leaf
  - Correspondence, 1815-1819 (Folder 2)
    - Letter, 7 May 1815, Bushrod Rust, Clairsville, to George Rust, Leesburg, Loudoun County, a; 2 pages
    - Letter, 13 December 1816, Armistead T. Mason, Washington, to George Rust, Philadelphia, b; 2 pages
    - Letter, 17 December 1816, Armistead T. Mason, Washington, to George Rust, Philadelphia, c; 2 pages
    - Letter, 22 March 1817, Armistead T. Mason, Rasberry Plain, to George Rust, Philadelphia, d; 2 pages
    - Letter, 1 November 1817, Armistead T. Mason, Leesburg, to Charles F. Mercer, [Leesburg], e; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 20 April 1818, Armistead T. Mason, n.p., to George Rust, Jr., Leesburg, f; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 15 January 1819, Armistead T. Mason, Selma, to George Rust, member of the Virginia Legislature, Richmond, g; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 6 February 1819, James Pleasants, Washington, to William S. Archer, House of Delegates, Richmond, h; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 15 April 1819, William H. Handey, n.p., to George Rust, Leesburg, confidential, i; 2 pages
  - Correspondence, 1820-1829 (Folder 3)
    - Letter, 8 December 1820, Joseph Lewis, Fredericksburg, to unknown correspondent, a; 2 pages
    - Letter, 22 December 1820, Joseph Lewis, Washington, to George Rust, House of Delegates, Richmond, b; 2 pages
    - Letter, 5 January 1821, R. H. Henderson, Leesburg, to George Rust, Jr., member of the House of Delegates, Richmond, c; 3 pages
    - Letter, 5 February 1822, R. I. Taylor, Alexandria, to George Rust, Richmond, d; 3 pages
    - Letter, 13 January 1824, Ben[?] Peyton, Richmond, to [George] Rust, n.p., e; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 13 January 1824, John Mason, Richmond, to [George] Rust, n.p., f; 2 pages
    - Letter, 13 January 1824,S. Slaughter, Richmond, to George Rust, Leesburg, Loudoun County, 2 pages
    - Letter, 16 February 1824, W. C. B. Butler, Colonel, 60th Regiment, Virginia militia, Fairfax Court House, to Gen. George Rust, n.p., h; 2 pages
    - Letter, 16 January 1828, Asa Rogers, Richmond, to Brigadier General George Rust, Loudoun County, i; 3 pages
    - Letter, 26 January 1828, George Rust, Richmond, to P. N. Nicholas, n.p., j; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 15 July 1829, from an anonymous correspondent, Charlestown, (West) Virginia, to Gen. George Rust, Leesburg, Loudoun County, k; 3 pages
  - Correspondence, 1830-1839 (Folder 4)
    - Letter, 11 March 1830, [George Rust, Jr.,], Superintendant's Office, United States Armory, Harper's Ferry [(West) Virginia], to Col. George Bomford, n.p., a; 3 pages
    - Letter, 27 March 1831, Edward Lucas, Jr., Richmond, to Dr. J. William Roper, Harper's Ferry, Jefferson County, (West) Virginia, 4 pages
    - Letter, 21 May 1832, Richard Norris, Baltimore, to Gen. [George] Rust, Harper's Ferry, c; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 4 August 1832, R. Withers, New York, to Gen. George Rust, Jr., Harper's Ferry, d; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 1 October 1833, W. G. Singleton, Winchester, to G. B. Wager, Charlestown, e; 2 pages
    - Letter, 21 March 1834, H. F. H., Leesburg, to unknown correspondent, f; 2 pages
    - Letter, 11 February 1837, Edward Lucas, Jr., House of Representatives, to Gen. George Rust, Harper's Ferry, g; 3 pages
    - Letter, 13 February 1837, Edward Lucas, Jr., House of Representatives, to George Rust, Harper's Ferry, h; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 14 February 1837, Richard Johnson, near Jefferson, to George Rust, Harper's Ferry, i; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 8 March 1837, George Rust, Washington, to L. Bullock, Philadelphia, j; 2 pages
    - Letter, 27 January 1838, Agnes Taylor, Upperville, to unknown correspondent, k; 2 pages
    - Letter, 9 March 1839, Amos Kendall, Washington, to George Rust, n.p., l; 1 leaf
  - Correspondence, 1840-1849 (Folder 5)
    - Letter, 27 June 1843, Clarence F. LeGrand, Plantation, Maryland Bend, Madison[?] Parish, Louisiana, to George Rust, Baltimore, a; 2 leaves
    - Letter, 28 January 1845, E. Mann, [Vicksburg?] to an unknown correspondent, b; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 5 March 1845,W. Selden, Washington, to [President James K. Polk], c; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 8 March 1845, J. Spaight, Washington, to James K. Polk, President of the United States, d; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 8 December 1849,R[obert] W[ard] Johnson, House of Representatives, to Harry Hill, New Orleans, Louisiana, e; 1 leaf
  - Correspondence, 1850-1853 (Folder 6)
    - Letter, 4 January 1850, Pierre Soule, Washington, to Trasimond Landry, Lieutenant Governor of Louisiana, New Orleans, a; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 4 January 1850, Pierre Soule, Washington, to Horace C. Cammack, New Orleans, b; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 12 December 1850, [R. Mills?], Gainston[?] [Louisiana], to George Rust, present, c; 2 pages
    - Letter, 4 February 1851, William M. Hume, Richmond, to William M. Rust, Eldorado, Arkansas, d; 3 pages
    - Letter, 20 November 1852, George W. Bolling, n.p., to William Allen, Claremont, e; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 25 February 1853, John H. Briscoe, Baltimore, to George Rust, United States Hotel, Washington, f; 3 pages
    - Letter, 2 March 1853 Andrew Keyser, House of Delegates, Richmond, to George Rust, Washington, g; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 8 March 1853 [George Rust], Washington, to the President of the United States [Franklin Pierce], h; 1 leaf
    - Letter, George Rust, United States Hotel [Washington], to the President of the United States [Franklin Pierce], two drafts, i; 5 leaves and 6 pages
    - Letter, 6 May 1853, G. M. Bayly and Company, New Orleans, to George Rust, Leesburg, Loudoun County, j; 2 pages
    - Letter, 1 June 1853, W. G. Singleton, Winchester, to unknown correspondent, k; 4 pages
    - Letter, 28 July 1853, L. P. Bayne, Washington, to Gen. [George Rust, Jr.], n.p., l; 3 pages
    - Letter, 1 December 1853, William Rust, New Orleans, to George [Rust], n.p., m; 2 pages
  - Correspondence, 1854-1856 (Folder 7)
    - Letter, 9 January 1854, Thomas Johnson, Greene County, to George Rust, Leesburg, Loudoun County, a; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 18 November 1854, L. P. Bayne, Washington, to Gen. [George Rust, Jr.], n.p., b; 2 pages
    - Letter, 3 February 1855, Joseph R. Snyder, Baltimore, to Judge John Moore, New Iberia, Louisiana, c; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 20 June 1855, Thomas Johnson, Henderson's Mill, Greene County, to George Rust, Leesburg, Loudoun County, d; 2 pages
    - Letter, 14 August 1855, A. Cochran, General Land Agency of A. Cochran, Council Bluffs, Iowa, to Gen. George Rust, n.p., e; 3 pages
    - Letter, 22 February 1856, B. C. Mason, Colrop, to Gen. [George Rust], n.p., f; 1 leaf
    - Letter, 7 March 1856, George Rust, Exeter, to Franklin Pierce, President of the United States, listing "persons from this [Loudoun] county now holding offices in Washington under the federal government, and opposed to your administration.", g; 3 pages
    - Letter, 11 October 1856,A[lbert] Rust, Alexandria, to Uncle [George Rust, Jr.], h; 4 pages
    - Letter, 14 October 1856,A[lbert] Rust, Howardsville, to Uncle [George Rust, Jr.], i; 4 pages
- Business papers, 1811-1858 (Folder 8)
  - Business papers, 1811-1858 (Folder 8)
    - account, 5 November 1811-16 May 1815 George Rust, Jr., with P. McIntyre, a; 2 pages
    - Promissory note, 1 January 1819, Armistead T. Mason to George Rust, b; 2 pages
    - Account, February-May 1831, John Weaver to George Rust, plank furnished, c; 1 leaf
    - Account, 5 April 1832, with George W. Carpenter's Chemical Warehouse, Philadelphia, d; 3 pages
    - Account, 1831-May 1832, Gen. George Rust, lumber borrowed from United States Armory, e; 2 pages
    - Letter, 1 June 1832,"Robison Cruso" to mechanics at Harper's Ferry, f; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 22 October 1832, Mess. Braden adn Rust from Wright and Brothers, umbrella manufactory in Philadelphia, g; 1 leaf
    - Account, 1 November 1832, with Hopkins Brothers, Baltimore, h; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 15 January 1836, Harper's Ferry post office to Gen. George Rust, i; 1 leaf
    - Tax receipt for 1834, paid 16 January 1836, Jefferson County (West) Virginia, j; 1 leaf
    - Promissory note, 19 November 1836, from Robert B. Rust to George Rust, also note, 20-21 February 1837, k; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 26 November 1836, from Thomas L. Jarrell to George Rust for payment for bricks, l; 1 leaf
    - tax receipt for 1836, paid 26 January 1838, Jefferson County (West) Virginia, m; 2 pages
    - Tax receipt for 1838, paid 22 November 1838, Loudoun County, Virginia, n; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 11 March 1841, to George Rust from Commissioners Burr W. Harrison and John A. Washington, sale of "Exeter" in Loudoun County, o; 1 leaf
    - Bond, 8 February 1847, George Rust to Loudoun County for release of a slave belonging to William Rust, seized to cover executions against William Rust, p; 1 leaf
    - Tax receipt, paid 3 December 1849, Loudoun County, q; 1 leaf
    - Broadside, September 1851, for thrashing machines and other farm equipment, G. Westinghouse and Company, r; 1 leaf
    - Insurance policy, 19 March 1852, no. 122817 to George Rust from the Washington County Mutual Insurance Company, s; 4 pages
    - Receipt, 13 October 1853, for Rust's subscription to the Loudoun Democrat, t; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 12 July 1854, G. H. Reese and Brothers, Baltimore, to George Rust, u; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 4 January 1855, from Alexandria, Loudoun, and Hampshire Railroad Company to George Rust, v; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 31 August 1855, from Alexandria, Loudoun, and Hampshire Railroad Company to George Rust, w; 1 leaf
    - Account, 2 May 1856, George Rust with Octavia Furr, x; 2 pages
    - List, 5 August 1856, of slaves and other property of George Rust and Abner Trundle at "Exeter" in Loudoun County now in Trundle's hands, y; 4 pages
    - Advertisements and receipts, 21 December 1858, for sale of slaves and property ("Indian Town" in Lancaster County, Virginia) in by D. J. Hartsook, trustee for George and Albert Rust, z; 2 leaves
    - Petition, n.d., of William Brannan for divorce from his wife Mary Reid Brannan, aa; 3 pages
    - letter, n.d., C. G. Wintersmith to George Rust, ab; 1 leaf
    - List, n.d., of slaves, ac; 2 pages
- Business papers, 1788, 1819-1858 (Folder 9-10)
  - Business papers, 1788, 1819-1837 (Folder 9)
    - Land patent, 20 October 1788, for 500 acres in Monongalia County, (West) Virginia, from Governor Edmund Randolph to Goldsmith Chandley assignee of James Holliday, assignee of John Overton, a; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 1 April 1819, from William T. T. Mason to George Rust, b; 1 leaf
    - Power of attorney, 22 May 1819, from president and directors of the Leesburg Turnpike Road Company to George Rust, c; 2 pages
    - Survey, 15 June 1819, of land in Leesburg, Virginia, owned by John Newton. Survey made by John J. Mathias, d; 2 pages
    - Deed, 1820, between George Rust on the one part and Thomas R. Mott and Samuel M. Edwards of the other, all of Loudoun County, for slaves, e; 2 pages
    - Account, 18 January 1820, George Rust with Jonathan Shepherd, f; 2 paged
    - Bond, 15 June 1820, George Rust to William T. T. Mason and Thomson Mason, g; 2 pages
    - Receipt, 7 December 1820, from William T. T. Mason to George Rust, h; 1 leaf
    - Copies, 26 February 1821, of vouchers filed in Virginia land office, i; 1 leaf
    - Notice, 23 February 1822, from the Mutual Assurance Society concerning Thomas W. Smith of Loudoun County, j; 1 leaf
    - Notice, 13 June 1827, that John H. Hughes has delivered a slave to George Rust, k; 2 pages
    - Agreement, September 1831, between George Rust and Robert Keyes on one part and John Mackell on the other for construction of a building at Harper's Ferry, l; 3 pages
    - Agreement, 1 October 1831, between George Rust and Robert Keyes on one part and John Weaver on the other for construction of a building at Harper's Ferry, m; 3 pages
    - Account, 9 April 1832, Messrs. Braden and Rust with A. Groverman and Son of Baltimore, Maryland, n; 2 pages
    - Receipt, 30 May 1832, from Daniel Lathhorn to George Rust for payment for carpentry work, o; 1 leaf
    - Bill of lading, 12 June 1832, for delivery of a box to Rust and Braden, p; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 3 July 1832, for delivery of a box to Braden and Rust at Harper's Ferry, q; 1 leaf
    - Account, 1 September 1832, with J. H. Brothers of Baltimore, r; 1 leaf
    - List, 1832, of salaries due at armory[?], s; 12 pages
    - Receipt, 1 February 1836, from G. W. Sappington for [L. T. A.?] Washington to George Rust for payment of execution against Rust by the court, t; 1 leaf
    - Tax receipt, 10 November 1836, Loudoun County, u; 1 leaf
    - Circular, 19 June 1837, from Virginia Board of Public Works regarding state proxies at all joint stock internal improvement companies, v; 1 leaf
  - Business papers, 1840-1858 (Folder 10)
    - Deed, 10 February 1840, of a business arrangement between George Rust of Loudoun County, and Francis D. Dungan and Thomas C. Watkins of Baltimore, Maryland, to go into the shoe and hat business, a; 8 pages
    - Account, 12 June 1843, George Rust with John Matthews, b; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 31 December 1844, from E. M. Kerr and Company of Baltimore to George Rust, c; 1 leaf
    - Memorandum, 30 June 1845, between George Rust, Francis D. Dungan, and Thomas C. Watkins, in which Rust sells his share of the business, d; 2 pages
    - Promissory note, 24 April 1846, from George Rust and Thomas H. Clagett to Burr W. Harrison and John A. Washington, e; 1 leaf
    - Agreement, 1 September 1847, between George Rust on one part and Daniel T. Fouche and Edward Hart on the other for construction on a house, f; 2 pages
    - Tax receipt, 27 November 1847, Loudoun County, g; 1 leaf
    - List, 21 November 1849, purchases made by George Rust of Alfred Rust's property, h; 2 pages
    - Receipt, 12 August 1850, Mountain House, Capon Springs, (West) Virginia, to George Rust, i; 1 leaf
    - Account, 23 August 1850, George Rust with B. B. Simpson, j; 1 leaf
    - Account, 1852, George Rust with S. M. Janney of the Springdale Boarding School for boarding Virginia Bedinger, k; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 7 February 1853, to George Rust from G. H. Reese and Brothers of Baltimore, l; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 12 March 1852, for subscription to Leesburg Washingtonian, m; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 23 December 1853, to George Rust from G. H. Reese and Brothers of Baltimore, n; 1 leaf
    - Advertisement, 1 June 1854, for sale of "Exeter" in Loudoun County, o; 2 pages
    - Receipt, 10 December 1853, to George Rust from G. H. Reese and Brothers of Baltimore, p; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, 18 January 1856, to George Rust from the Exchange Hotel in Richmond, Virginia, q; 1 leaf
    - Agreement, 3 October 1856, between D. J. Hartsook, as attorney for Mary W. Cabell, and George Rust and Albert Rust, regarding the Rusts' purchase of "Indian Town" in Lancaster County, Virginia, r; 2 pages
    - Deed, 3 October 1856, between D. J. Hartsook, attorney for Mary W. Cabell, on one part and George Rust and Albert Rust on the other, for purchase of "Indian Town," 1620 acres, s; 2 pages
    - Deed, 3 October 1856, between George Rust and Albert Rust on one part and D. J. Hartsook and R. W. Elsom on the other for "Indian Town," 1620 acres, until purchase money is paid, t; 3 pages
    - Agreement, 21 September 1858, between D. J. Hartsook, agent for Albert Rust and George Rust's executors and devisees, on one part and William C. Carroll on the other for Carroll's purchase of "Indian Town", u; 4 pages
    - Agreement, 19 October 1858, between A. T. M. Rust and George T. Rust, executors of George Rust, on one part and Albert Rust on the other, for settling George Rust's and Albert Rust's partnership, v; 8 pages
    - List, n.d., of slaves at "Indian Town", w; 2 pages
    - list, n.d., of servants at "Indian Town", x; 2 pages
    - List, n.d., of slaves, no location, y; 1 leaf
    - List, n.d., of slaves, no location, z; 1 leaf
    - Calling card, n.d., for Miss Faulkner, aa; 1 leaf
    - Calling card, n.d., for Annie H. Faulkner, ab; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, n.d., from Strothers Hotel to George Rust, ac; 1 leaf
    - Receipt, n.d., from Strothers Hotel, ad; 1 leaf
    - Account, n.d., George Rust with John Weaver, ae; 2 pages